A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests, Series D FA313
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests, Series D
1899-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
China Medical Board (U.S)
Spelman family
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine)
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Rockefeller, John D.
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Rockefeller family
Spelman Fund
Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.)
Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Davison Fund
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller Foundation
Standard Oil Company
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
Rockefeller, David
Rockefeller, Winthrop
Sealantic Fund, New York
Rockefeller University
International Education Board
FA313
54 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research except where particular restrictions are noted.
Material in the Rockefeller family collections which provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net worth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; C Business Interests; D Civic Interests; E Cultural Interests; F Economic Reform Interests; G Educational Interests; H Friends and Services; I Homes; J Housing Interests; K Medical Interests; L Real Estate; M Maps and Memorabilia; N Religious Interests; O Rockefeller Boards; P Welfare - General Files; Q World Affairs; R Welfare - Youth Files; S Documents; T Public Relations; U Public Land Law Review Commission; V Greenrock; W Properties; X Costume Collection; Y Media; Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal; AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller; AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in multiple sections, generally in alphabetical order:
American Institute of Criminal Law and Criminology; Association of the Bar; Bureau of Municipal Research; Citizens Union of the City of New York; Citizens Budget Commission; Civic Leagues; Civil Service Reform Association; National Civil Service League; Constitutional League of America; Democracy; Fire Companies; Grand Army of the Republic; Highways; Juries; League of Women Voters; Mayor's Committee; New York City and New York State; People's Institute; Pocantico Hills (NY) Lyceum; Hope Chapel Community House, Tarrytown (NY); Police; Political Organizations; Russell Sage Foundation; Regional Planning Association Research; Tarrytown (NY) Projects; United States Government; Westchester County (NY) Charter; Westchester County (NY) Research Bureau; Westchester County (NY) Organizations.
Scope and Contents note
This series reflects primarily the activities of John D. Rockefeller, Jr., but significant documentation on the political and civic concerns of each of his sons is also present. In addition to extensive files on family support of the Republican Party on the national, state, and local level, separate folders exist on specific candidates, such as President Dwight D. Eisenhower, New York City Mayor Fiorello La Guardia, and New York Governor Thomas Dewey. There are substantial files on family support for Nelson Rockefeller during his first gubernatorial campaign and immediately afterward. However, very little material exists in this series on his presidential effort in 1960.
The files on Rockefeller involvement with "good" government groups is, from an historical point of view, at least as significant as the political files. Organizations such as the Bureau of Municipal Research and the National Civic Federation provided the personnel and the theoretical underpinnings for the revolution in government which occurred during the course of the twentieth century. Rockefeller involvement with these groups through the end of the 1950s is well documented in this series.
Civic involvement of a different nature is also to be found in this series. The family's concern for an involvement with the problems and organizations of Tarrytown, Westchester County, and New York City constitute a large portion of this series. These are primarily relationships with local fire departments, grand juries, transportation departments, and police.
Finally, Nelson Rockefeller's service in the administration of President Franklin D. Roosevelt and President Dwight D. Eisenhower, and John D. Rockefeller 3rd's participation in the Japanese Peace Treaty negotiations in 1951 are included in this series.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include:
FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Parks -- New York (State); New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Medical sciences; Medical research; Medical education; Medical care; Maternal health services; Juvenile delinquency; International relations -- United States; International relations; International education; International economic relations; International cooperation; Civic improvement; Child welfare; Public health administration; Public policy; Prohibition; Public health; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; Performing arts; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Philanthropy; Urban renewal; Urban policy; World War II; World War I; Housing rehabilitation; Public relations; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Health insurance; Folk art; Government policy; Family planning; Federal government -- United States; Travel; United States; Philanthropy -- United States; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Religious institutions; Restoration and conservation; Public welfare; Religion; Arts; Business; Business enterprises, Foreign; Capital investments; Charitable contributions; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charities; Charities -- Investments; Education -- United States; Education; Economics; Economic policy; Economic development; Art; Art, Modern; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Rockefeller Center; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- )
- American Institute of Criminal Law and Criminology
  - American Institute of Criminal Law and Criminology, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Some reports on work of Institute. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledges $10,000, paid. J. B. Reynolds real spirit of institute, died in 1923 - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s connection ceased. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., James Bronson, Raymond B. Fosdick.
    File Plan note
    115
- Association of the Bar
  - Association of the Bar, 1919-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Requests for endowment declined. Work of association. Thomas M. Debevoise's membership. John D. Rockefeller 3rd made contributions toward study to improve administration of justice in New York in 1953. Other gifts. Papers prepared for the Association by New York attorneys. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas M. Debevoise, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, John E. Lockwood, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    21
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also Box 54.
  - Association of the Bar - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1947-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller gives $20,000 toward study of justice with respect to problems of the family. Study panel urges single city court for family cases. John D. Rockefeller 3rd's contribution toward Court Revision Activities Gellhorn study. Public interest through play "The Maze. Laurance S. Rockefeller gift, Socony Mobil Oil stock. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, John E. Lockwood, Allen T. Klots, Edwin T. Chinlund, D. B. Bonsal.
  - Association of the Bar - Mayors Committee on the Courts, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller member of committee. Chairman of subcommittee on Youth, Family and Children's Matters. Left committee in 1959. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Allen T. Klots.
    21.3
  - Association of the Bar - Children and Families in the Courts - Volume I, March 1953 (Box 54, Folder 400)
    Report to the Special Committee to Study the Administration of Law Relating to the Family, Association of the Bar of the City of New York. Report prepared by Walter Gellhorn, assisted by Jacob D. Hyman and Sidney H. Asch. Report was for committee use only and was not published.
    See also Box 1, Folders 2-4.
  - Association of the Bar - Children and Families in the Courts - Volume II, March 1953 (Box 54, Folder 401)
- Bureau of Municipal Research
  - Bureau of Municipal Research - Correspondence and Contributions, 1905-1911 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Brief for the establishment of an Institute for Municipal research, budget campaign, activities of Bureau, purchase Chicago Vice Commission reports, letter to Congressman Fitzgerald urging appropriation for Commission on Economy and Efficiency. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, R. F. Cutting, W. Allen.
    82, 82A
  - Bureau of Municipal Research - Correspondence and Contributions, 1911-1917 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Better Business Bureau of New York City, 1922-1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Small Rockefeller gifts to organization. No initiative shown in this office toward Bureau. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard.
    82.1
  - Bureau of Municipal Research - Police Inquiry, 1912-1914 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Investigation of Police Department, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution to Bureau for that purpose, publication of report, Pension Fund study. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., W. Allen, J. Greene, Starr J. Murphy, H. Bruere.
    See also Bureau of Social Hygiene collection.
  - Bureau of Municipal Research - School Inquiry, 1912-1914 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Plans for inquiry into public schools of New York City, appointment of Committee members, selection of Mr. Greene. Reports on the organization and methods of the Board of Education, and on school system in New York City. Plans to establish an educational fund for promotion of efficiency in school administration. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, W. Allen, Jerome Greene, J. Dewey, J. P. Mitchel.
    82.2
  - Bureau of Municipal Research - Training School for Public Services, 1910-1920 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Scope and organization of school for public administrators, suggested subjects for scientific research. Fund for training men. List of contributors and contributions. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. 's contributions. Correspondents include C. A. Beard, W. Allen, Starr J. Murphy, P Willard S. Richardson, J. Greene, G. W. Perkins, Mrs. E. H. Harriman.
    82.3
    See also Box 40, Folder 318.
  - Institute for Public Service, 1916-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    176
  - Cities Census Committee, 1920-1940 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution to survey and 1922 budget, tabulation of data compiled. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Raymond B. Fosdick, Dr. Haven Emerson.
    82.6
- Citizens Union of the City of New York
  - Citizens Union of the City of New York, 1901-1935 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Began as union of anti-Tammany element, modified to straight good government program. Election struggle, 1913. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made $100 annual contributions, later increased to $200, $300, plus special gifts. $400 annual gifts in 1930s for all purposes. Rockefeller staff supported idea, did not initiate anything. In 1940s, Union moved toward city planning, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest declined. Requests for contributions. Discussion of program. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Nelson A. Rockefeller made small annual contributions. Invitations to dinners declined. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates, Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel, Nelson A. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    58
  - Citizens Union of the City of New York, 1936-1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Began as union of anti-Tammany element, modified to straight good government program. Election struggle, 1913. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made $100 annual contributions, later increased to $200, $300, plus special gifts. $400 annual gifts in 1930s for all purposes. Rockefeller staff supported idea, did not initiate anything. In 1940s, Union moved toward city planning, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest declined. Requests for contributions. Discussion of program. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Nelson A. Rockefeller made small annual contributions. Invitations to dinners declined. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates, Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Citizens Union of the City of New York, 1936-1950 (Box 3, Folder 0014A)
    Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Citizens Union of the City of New York, 1951-1961 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Citizens Union of the City of New York, 1951-1961 (Box 3, Folder 0015A)
  - Citizens Union of the City of New York - Searchlight Dinner - Lincoln Center, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd attended dinner. Presented Lincoln Center program. Answered questions.
  - Citizens Union of the City of New York - Contributions, 1951-1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    For Searchlight dinner tickets. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions to Voters' Directory. Correspondents include Charles J. Hardy, William Zeckendorf.
  - Citizens Union of the City of New York - Clippings, 1950-1960 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Clippings, 1950-1960. Voters Directory.
- Citizens Budget Commission
  - Citizens Budget Commission, 1932-1961 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Watchdog on city expenses. Represented real estate owners in the majority. Survey - City Administration undertaken at Mayor O'Dwyer's request. Fought to raise subway fare. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s yearly contributions. Membership list. Plaque offered to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. John D. Rockefeller 3rd gets award. de V. O. Smith comment. Correspondents include Jay Downer, Arthur W. Packard, Thomas M. Debevoise, Yorke Allen, Robert W. Dowling, de V. O. Smith, A. D. Leidesdorf, John M. Leavens, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    58.1
  - Citizens Budget Commission, 1932-1961 (Box 4, Folder 0019A)
    David Rockefeller gets Civic Service medal. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Citizens Budget Commission - Harry Klein, 1932-1951 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Lawyer distributes pamphlet attacking Rockefeller family.
  - Citizens Budget Commission - Contributions, 1932-1950 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Raymond B. Fosdick recommended, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made annual contributions, $1,000 to $5,000. H. P. Fish report. Contributions reduced in 1941. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Peter Grimm, Robert W. Dowling.
  - Citizens Budget Commission - Contributions, 1932-1950 (Box 4, Folder 0021A)
    David Rockefeller contributions. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Citizens Budget Commission - Contributions, 1950-1961 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Citizens Budget Commission - Contributions, 1950-1961 (Box 4, Folder 0022A)
- Civic Leagues
  - Civic Leagues - National Civic Federation, 1914-1948 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Organization formed to study Socialist's objectives and tactics. Mr. Easley's leadership, death. Later correspondence. Correspondents include Frederick T. Gates, Starr J. Murphy, Ralph M. Easley, Raymond B. Fosdick, Thomas M. Debevoise, M. W. Beeks.
    120
  - Civic Leagues - National Civic Federation - Contributions, 1900-1919 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions.
  - Civic Leagues - Civic League of Cleveland, 1903-1918 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    Formerly called Municipal Association. Clean politics, good government. John D. Rockefeller contributed to current expenses but not to special drives. Discontinued contributions in 1918. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller Jr., Starr J. Murphy.
    120C
  - Civic Leagues - Womens Civic League of Tarrytown, 1911-1939 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    Appeals for contributions. History of League. No real Rockefeller interest after 1930 although contributions continued. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, Mrs. J. A. Bolles, Mrs. H. Wall.
    120W
- Civil Service Reform Association
  - Civil Service Reform Association, 1902-1937 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Watchdog over Civil Service practices and policies in state. John D. Rockefeller contributed to 1919, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. after. Routine contributions. Handled by Arthur W. Packard in 30's. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard.
    42
  - Civil Service Reform Association, 1939-1960 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Civil Service Reform Association - Contributions - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1938-1947 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    Annual contributions made by John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Civil Service Reform Association - Contributions - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1947-1959 (Box 6, Folder 30)
- National Civil Service League
  - National Civil Service League, 1915-1959 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    Objective was to gain business-like administration of government through a well qualified civil service. Nominal Rockefeller interest in work of League expressed through Office. No initiative, contributions small. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made annual contributions: 1922-1930, $500; 1930-1932, $300; 1932-1936, $1,000. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur Young, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - National Civil Service League - Contributions, 1937-1942 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    Contributions list, 1922-1954. Merit system. Correspondents include Nicholas Kelly, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Winthrop Rockefeller, Frank W. Abrams.
  - National Civil Service League - Contributions, 1942-1959 (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Constitutional League of America
  - Constitutional League of America, 1920-1922 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    Organized to present the Constitution to the people of America. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions. Director J. A. Myers was also connected with the Repeal organization. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s 1922 pledge of $5,000 to League misappropriated by Myers for himself. Money finally returned to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, J. A. Myers.
    80.1
- Democracy
  - Democracy - Americanism, 1940-1949 (Box 7, Folder 35)